"Is Shrimp Good for You?
Pollutants and Food Safety"
Over a decade ago, farmed shrimp
overtook wild-caught,
such that by 2016, two-thirds
of global shrimp production
was farmed.
The main potential
food safety hazards
of shrimp farming
are infectious disease,
chemical contamination,
and veterinary drug residues.
In terms of mercury,
shrimp is the second
leading source,
but it's still far behind tuna.
In terms of banned pesticides,
flame retardants,
and polycyclic
aromatic hydrocarbons,
there are some
significant concerns
regarding human health risks
associated with
shrimp consumption.
Safety limits were exceeded
for banned pesticides
Chlordane, DDT, heptachlor,
aldrin, dieldrin,
and endosulfan.
Now, this was based
on worst case scenario values,
but on the other hand,
based on just eating
three and a half grams
of shrimp a day,
which is like a single shrimp,
or one serving of shrimp
every two weeks or so.
Eating just one shrimp
could give you as much
as 50 times more DDT
than is considered safe.
Same with flame retardant
chemicals
and same with naphthalene
and benzopyrene.
For PFAS forever chemicals,
eating the highest levels
of the most contaminated shrimp
could pose a health risk,
which comes out to be about
a serving a day.
Shrimp can also
be a substantial source
of carcinogenic
heterocyclic amines,
which is typically seen
in dry heat cooked chicken,
like baked, grilled,
fried, or broiled.
Levels for shrimp
were in the 10 to 50 range,
which is what you start
to see with chicken grilled
at over 400 degrees Fahrenheit
(200+ °C).
Note that steaming,
or presumably boiling
or other moist cooking methods,
are the safest ways
to cook meat.
Another issue with shrimp
is foodborne illness,
even with precooked
ready-to-eat shrimp,
which have been found
to be an international vehicle
of antibiotic-resistant
bacteria.
As shrimp farming
has gotten more intensive,
there is an increased occurrence
of disease problems
as a direct result
of the higher stocking densities
at shrimp farms,
causing stress-initiated disease
and rapid transmission
of infectious diseases,
and along with more disease
comes more use of antibiotics
and disinfectant chemicals
to keep the animals
from dying prematurely.
In India, where most
of the shrimp eaten
in the United States comes from,
90% of the bacteria tested
were resistant
to three or more classes
of antibiotics.
Thus, shrimp could serve
as delivery vehicles
of antimicrobial resistance
to pathogenic bacteria
to consumers
and from country to country.
Thirteen brands
of ready-to-eat shrimp
from four countries of origin
were obtained
from local grocery stores
in the U.S.,
and 80% of the bacterial species
picked up
were antibiotic resistant,
and that included numerous
resistant human pathogens
such as E. coli and Salmonella.
Foodborne pathogens were found
in every single sample tested.
And most of those
contained multiple pathogens.
Ready-to-eat shrimp are sold
with instructions
to just thaw before serving,
which may also result
in consumer exposure
to antibiotic-resistant
bacteria.
Enterococci are used as markers
of fecal contamination
of food products.
At a retail level,
about 85% of ground beef
and turkey are contaminated
with fecal bacteria
and about half of chicken
and a third of pork.
Sampling more than 700 shrimp
at grocery outlets
in eight states
across the United States,
researchers found
that approximately
two-thirds of the shrimp samples
were contaminated
with fecal bacteria.
And in terms
of antimicrobial resistance
in U.S. retail seafood,
shrimp had the highest odds
of being contaminated,
and the risk
was about twice as high
in farm-raised shrimp
compared to wild-caught shrimp.
A small percentage
were even resistant
to a carbapenem antibiotic,
which is considered
an antibiotic of last resort.
In the hospital, we used
to call it gorillacillin.
It's also been found
in Canadian shrimp,
linked to a farming operation
in India,
our number one source
of shrimp imports,
and others traced back
to Vietnam and Ecuador,
other major shrimp importers
into the United States.
So, shrimp farms
may be a key reservoir
of antibiotic resistance genes,
which may pose a significant
threat to public health.
When we consume shrimp,
we may also be consuming
those antibiotic
resistance genes,
which can be passed along
to human pathogens
in our own body.
Resistance genes have been
detected in shrimp products
destined for human consumption,
but what about
the antibiotics themselves?
Are there residues
of antibiotic drugs
left in shrimp
at a retail level?
That's what I'll cover, next.